# MICHAEL NSIAH-NIMO, M.Sc.

DATA PROFESSIONAL | RESEARCH AND BUSINESS ANALYTICS



#### CONTACT



Lincoln, Nebraska



michael20129648@gmail.com



in <u>Linkedin</u>

#### EDUCATION

**MSc Statistics** 

Master's Thesis: Sample Size Estimation for Linear Mixed Models with Dependent End Points

#### **University of Texas at El Paso**

2015 - 2017

**BSc Actuarial Science** 

### **Kwame Nkrumah University** of Science and Technology

2010 - 2014

#### EXPERT LEVEL SKILLS

- Programming & Development: Python (7+ years), R (6+ years), SAS (5+ years), Jupyter Notebook, Visual Studio Code, Spyder, Git, Microsoft Office Suite (Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Access, Outlook)
- Data Cleaning & Manipulation: Python (Pandas, NumPy), R (Tidyverse, dplyr), SQL, Data Wrangling Techniques, Feature Engineering & Dimensionality Reduction (PCA, t-
- Statistical & Machine Learning Tools: Python (statsmodels, Scikit-Learn, Pytorch), R (glm, Imer), etc.
- Databases & Data Storage: SQL Server, Google BigQuery, Amazon S3, Snowflake, REDCap, QuestionPro, Hadoop Ecosystem
- Data Visualization: Tableau, Power BI, Python (Seaborn, Matplotlib), R (ggplot2, Shiny)
- Operating Systems: UNIX, WINDOWS
- Study Design & Optimization: Observational & Experimental Designs, Clinical Trials, Regression Techniques, Classification Methods, A/B Testing, Randomized Controlled Trials, Hypothesis Testing
- Robustness & Validation: Advanced Sampling Schemes, Sample Size Estimation, Power Analysis, Cross-Validation, Residual Analysis, Accuracy Metrics, Bootstrap Methods
- Multivariate & Causal Analysis: General Linear Models (GLM), Bayesian LASSO Models, Multi-Level & Survival Analysis, Longitudinal Data, Time Series, Propensity Score Matching, Instrumental Variable Analysis
- Algorithmic Modeling & Machine Learning: Gradient Boosting, Neural Networks, Random Forest, SVM, Ensemble Methods, Decision Trees, K-Nearest Neighbors, Clustering (K-Means, Hierarchical)

#### DATA MANAGEMENT, COMPLAINCE AND REPORTING

- Data Management: Missing Data Analysis, Outlier Detection, Feature Scaling, Normalization, Encoding, Clean Dataset Creation, Summary Tables, Data Listings
- Compliance & Standards: Regulatory Adherence (EMA, ICH, CDISC, IRB, HIPAA, PHI), NIH/NIMHD Guidelines, Statistical Analysis Plans (SAPs), Regulatory Submissions
- Reporting & Interpretation: Model Interpretation, Hypothesis Testing, Report Writing, Dynamic Dashboards, Publication-Ready Manuscripts, Conference Presentations

#### PROFILE

Over the past 7 years, I have developed expertise in designing and adapting statistical, machine learning/AI, deep learning, prevalence informatics, and data visualization models focused on business, healthcare, and marketing outcomes. I've consulted on over 100 projects across healthcare, industry, and consumer services, simplifying complex challenges to drive organizational success and profitability.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

#### Staff Research Scientist | Research and Business Analytics

University of Texas at El Paso, Integrative Analytic Unit

JULY 2020 - PRESENT

- · Design and execute advanced statistical analyses for observational and experimental studies, including sampling strategies, recruitment methodologies, and sample size calculations, ensuring precise and reliable results that enhanced study validity and credibility
- Lead a team of 7 statisticians and data scientists to develop a deep learning model to create risk indices using storyboarding and data visualization tools to predict and track business risk levels, market and consumer trends, and financial disparities in relationship to the Hispanic population affecting industrial and retail production (MAD: 8 years, R =0.92, p value <0.0001)
- Direct and manage comprehensive exploratory data analyses, hypothesis testing and statistical modeling for federal grant projects, informing model building and significantly advancing research in socioeconomic disparities and finical metrics of insurance and billing costs related to financial inequity across the US-Mexico Borderplex , leading to the successful acquisition of over \$2 million in research funding
- Manage and lead over 10 financial/business analysts, data engineers, and professional faculty to design and build business risk assessment and stratification models utilizing neural networks and tree models , contributing to a 25% reduction in operational risks and a 20% in crease in project funding, enhancing financial outcomes for the research enterprise
- Develop reliable and reusable Python scripts across diverse business and large upscale industrial projects for numeric and text preprocessing, assessing data drift distribution across time points, driving transformative changes including a 40% increasing data processing efficiency and a 30% reduction in data storage costs
- Develop and integrate Bayesian analysis with frequentist hypothesis testing, model evaluation in measuring economic factors and relevant population features in randomized studies for federal grant applications boosting a remarkable 30% reduction in the related costs
- Conducted A/B tests to identify relevant metrics and timelines to boost and extend strategic financial, and business initiatives, resulting in a 35% increase in extramural grant funding, a 25% boost in stakeholder advertisement reach, and a 20% rise in philanthropic support.
- Analyze and mine diverse datasets and customer surveys to advance records, marketing data, and outreach economic indicators from a relational database using advanced SQL and python pandas queries to generate actionable insights; advancing research and stakeholders objectives effectively.

#### Data Scientist | Statistician | Analytics

University of Texas at El Paso, College of Science, Research Enterprise

JULY 2018 - JULY 2020

- Conducted time series analysis and forecasting on expenses, revenue, and grant funding data, resulting in improved financial planning and resource allocation strategies
- Formulated and applied mathematical models and other optimizing methods to develop and interpret information that assists management with decision making, policy formulation, and other functions associated with the College of Science research enterprise.
- Worked on diverse datasets, leveraging both parametric and non-parametric statistical methodologies for federal and philanthropic foundation grants and increasing external funding
- Developed comprehensive metrics to serve as financial determinants, analyzing key issues such as revenue, expenditure, and extramural funding performance, market trends, and economic disparities in the Borderplex region
- Used SQL, Tableau, and MapBox to extract, model, and visualize demographic data from El Paso County, assessing socioeconomic divides within zip codes and their related financial implications boosting targeted grant applications for economic disparity research by 50%.

#### **Statistics and Data Science Intern**

University of Texas at El Paso, Center for Institutional, Research and Planning

SUMMER 2018

- · Collaborated with a team of researchers on multiple project planning, design, and analysis to address institutional and educational policy issues at UTEP
- · Contributed expertise in mining higher educational research databases which generated reports focused on institutional research end products
- Facilitated academic publications presentations utilizing Big Data for institutional research and university stakeholders

# MICHAEL NSIAH-NIMO, M.Sc.

#### DATA PROFESSIONAL | RESEARCH AND BUSINESS ANALYTICS

#### **Behavioral Skills**

- Ability to convey complex machine learning and statistical concepts to non-technical stakeholders, fostering understanding and collaboration.
- Proven track record of seamless collaboration across interdisciplinary teams, contributing to project success.
- Adept in identifying challenges and implementing innovative solutions ensuring the integrity of the analyses.
- Experience in providing guidance and mentorship to junior team members fostering a collaborative work environment.
- Flexibility with changing priorities, strong attention to detail, ability to work well under pressure and take on unfamiliar tasks

#### COURSES & CERTIFICATIONS

#### **Standford Online**

- Advanced Learning Algorithms
- Supervised Machine Learning Regression and Classification
- Unsupervised Machine Learning
- · Reinforcement Learning

#### **Duke University Online**

- · Inferential Statistics
- Probability and Data with Python and R
- Generalized Linear Models ( Linear regression and Modeling)

#### **IBM Devops**

Continuous Integration and Continuous Delivery (CI/CD)
 DevOps · Agile Methodologies · Cloud-Native Architecture · Unit Testing · Infrastructure as code (IaC) · Automated Continuous Deployment · Microservices

## DSI Data Science Professional Certification Actionable Learnings:

- Learned how to extract & manipulate data using SQL.
   Application, Python for statistical concepts such as hypothesis tests for measuring the effect of AB Tests
- Applied data preparation steps for ML including missing values, categorical variable encoding, outliers, feature scaling, feature selection & model validation
- Utilized Machine Learning and Deep Learning algorithms for regression, classification, clustering, association rule learning, and causal impact analysis for measuring the impact of an event over time
- Deployed ML pipelines onto a live website using Streamlit and adapted Github for version control and collaboration
- Utilized Tableau to create powerful Data Visualizations and turn business problems into Data Science solutions

# PROFESSIONAL CONFERENCES

- Microsoft Al Research Forum, 2024
- University of Hawaii Bioinformatics Data Science Workshops, 2023
- NIH NIGMS Cloud Based Biomedical Research, 2023
- Better Data for More Equitable Research: Research America Alliance, 2023
- RCMI Seminars at Meharry Medical College, 2023
- College of Science Stakeholders' on Health Disparities and Cancer Research, 2016, 2017, 2018, 2019, 2020, 2021, 2022, 2023
- JSM Conference 2017, Diversity Scholar
- Cardwell Foundation Seminar, 2016

#### Lecturer/Research Statistician

University of Texas at El Paso

AUGUST 2015 - JULY 2018

- Collaborated with Dr. Amy Wagler on multiple statistical research projects, leading to advancements in statistical methodologies that improved data interpretation and contributed to manuscripts reviewed for publications.
- Applied Design of Experiments (DOE) techniques to clinical data analysis, increasing
  experimental accuracy and reliability by 20%, resulting in more consistent and valid
  research outcomes.
- Instructed over 150 students in advanced mathematics, achieving a 90% pass rate while
  mentoring students on end-of-semester projects, enhancing their understanding and
  application of statistical techniques in real-world scenarios.
- Assisted in developing and publishing a novel statistical method for calculating sample sizes for multiple hypotheses in linear mixed model settings. This method produced nonconservative bounds compared to the Bonferroni method, increasing research efficiency
- Created and managed advanced statistical codes using R , SAS ad Python software for data cleaning, validation, analysis, and report generation, streamlining data processes and reducing analysis time by 40%

#### **BUSINESS PROJECTS**

#### **Enhancing Targeting Accuracy Using ML**

 Built a model that would accurately predict the customers that would sign up for a delivery club. This allowed for a much more targeted approach when running the next iteration of the campaign (Accuracy: KNN = 0.936, RF = 0.935, Logistic Regression = 0.866)

#### **Predicting Customer Loyalty Using ML**

 Built a predictive model using Random Forest in Python to estimate customer loyalty scores for a company's data agency leading to a 30% increase in the ability to contact customers with promotional material (4-Fold CV R-squared: Random Forest = 0.925, Decision Tree = 0.871)

#### "You Are What You Eat" Customer Segmentation

 Used k-means clustering on grocery transaction data to split out customers into distinct "shopper types" to accurately target customers with relevant content & promotions

#### Understanding Alcohol Product Relationships Using Association Rule Learning

 Utilized Association Rule Learning to analyze transactional relationships and dependencies between products in the alcohol section of a grocery store, resulting in a 20% increase in cross-selling effectiveness and a 15% boost in overall revenue.

#### Fruit Classification Using A Convolutional Neural Network

 Built & optimized a Convolutional Neural Network to classify images of fruits, with the goal of helping a grocery retailer enhance & scale their sorting & delivery processes.

#### Compressing Feature Space For Classification Using PCA

- Applied Principal Component Analysis (PCA) to reduce the dimensionality of 50 cytokines to capture variation in estimated biological ages among Hispanic Origin Individuals leading to an increase in model performance
- Used Principal Component Analysis (PCA) to compress 100 unlabelled, sparse features into a more manageable number for classifying buyers of Ed Sheeran's latest album.

#### Quantifying Sales Uplift With Causal Impact Analysis

Analyzed customer retail practices to quantify the increase in sales attributed to customers
joining the company's delivery club compared to what they would have spent without the
club. This analysis revealed a significant 41.1% uplift in sales among club members,
indicating the club's positive impact on customer spending

#### Development of an Inflammatory Aging Clock (iAge) for Individuals of Hispanic Origin

 Developed a biological age metric engineered from sociobehavioral surveys and molecular data utilizing artificial neural networks and auto-encoded features modeling and tracking health and insurance billing and financial outcomes in health disparities

#### Professional Contributions to Financial and Healthcare Federal and Non - Federal Grants Projects

NIH Project No: 5U54MD007592 -27, SUB IDS: 8320, 8321, 8317 NIH Project No: 5U54MD007592 -29, SUB IDS: 8320, 8321, 8317 NIH Project No: 1C060D032074-01 & 3U54CA272167-02S1

- National Institute of Health (NIH) U54's for the College's Research Core :
- NIH All of Us Data for Preliminary Data for Health Disparities Research
- NIH U54 Clinical Research
- NIH U54 Socio behavioral Research
- NIH Covid 19 U54 Supplements
- NIH C06 Grants for the Borderplex Biomedical Research Core
- NIMHD Grants for Health Disparities, RCMI Grants for Hispanic Health Disparities
- Paso Del Norte Health Research Grants